Back in April 2020, oil prices went
negative after the futures market had
completely underestimated the collapse
in demand, causing market participants
to have to scramble to find places to
unload all the oil that they purchased.
Here in April 2026,
the futures market is in danger of
something similar, but in the opposite
direction after market participants once
again maybe completely underestimating
the collapse in supply. Fearing that
might be the case, Dallas Federal
Reserve went out and asked Texas oil
industry veterans what they thought
about what's going on in the oil
situation, and what they found
you're not going to like.
There is a historic, yet almost
completely unappreciated disconnect
between cash prices and futures market
prices of petroleum. We never saw
anything like this in the Gulf War in
1990, nothing close even in 2022 during
the Ukraine invasion. It's gotten to be
like there are two oil markets with
seemingly little relationship from one
to the other. Now, that has enormous
implications, just starting with
people's impressions of how everything
is going, what the chances for real
fallout in the real economy really are.
If all you see is the futures price like
WTI or front month Brent, it looks like
the entire energy marketplace is
relatively optimistic. Now, $96 a barrel
WTI futures isn't exactly good, but it
also isn't 130, which is what traders
are paying for actual barrels today. But
here's the thing.
The real world is increasingly being
forced toward the spot price rather than
the futures price. Just look at
gasoline. Wholesale gasoline in the US
just hit a new multi-year high, and over
the past couple of weeks, it's really
started to diverge from WTI futures,
moving in the direction of cash
real-world petroleum costs. And if or
when retail pump prices begin to reflect
the other oil market that no one's
paying attention to, at least not right
now, the entire perception of the
situation will flip drastically.
So, Steve, we got a lot of stuff going
on in energy, of course, as people know,
but I think there's a lot of
misconceptions and understandable
misconceptions about what's really
taking place here because it really does
start with the fact that the closure of
Hormuz has locked up
an incomprehensible level of supply. I
think that's the part that's really
under under appreciated if not
completely unappreciated. The amount of
supply that has been taken off the
market is
staggering, beyond comprehensive. Uh so,
the answer the question here is um what
do we look at as far as assessing what
that's going to do to the global economy
and beyond?
>> Yeah, that that that is a real question,
Jeff, because we look out through in the
past and we can say, "Hey, four out of
the last five recessions were all energy
shocks." So, if you're long the market
right now and say, "Hey, I think it's
going to go higher," then you know at
some point it's going to reverse. And if
you're actually kind of de-risked during
the last drop in the market, and you're
like, "I don't want to play chase, but
is this thing got some legs where I need
to or is this thing about to drop off?"
Because that's the real risk. We know
the longer energy prices stay up, we
know that consumers cannot afford them.
Now, in the short run, we do know tax
checks are higher. It's helping offset
some of this, but over time, the longer
the shock goes, consumer spending has to
drop. And then you couple with the fact
that what are we hearing from the
factory sector right now? "Hey, it's
booming." But it's booming cuz we're
inventory building. And that's a huge
red flag. So, once again, we're front
running things, we're building up
inventory, and we're trying to look out
and say, "Hey, how can we time this as
the market's going up?" Because we know
the odds are high that we're going to
get a recession, perhaps a crisis, and
we know the equity markets are going to
come down. The problem is, Jeff, we look
at the equity markets right now, and
it's at all-time highs and continuing to
go higher. And yet, you're hearing
everyone around the world, central
bankers, you're hearing investment
banks, analysts, you know, the pros are
all saying this can't last, but the
reality is for the short-term it is. And
yet, that I think that's the real
question here is how long can consumers
go? And right now, we're not seeing any
crash. We're hearing complaints, but the
spending hasn't dropped off yet.
>> That's the point, right, Steve? It's how
sticky the oil shock will end up being.
I hate to use that term cuz it's
overused by economists, but that's
really the issue. It's how long will oil
prices linger around closer to the cash
price rather than the futures price. And
we'll talk about it in a minute why the
why there's such a difference there.
But that's that's the issue. Like you
said, Steve, in the short run, we've got
a couple of positives, a couple of
tailwinds. One of them being in the
United States anyway, you've got the tax
refund payments, which are right now a
lot of a lot of the studies including
the retail sales data itself from the
month of March suggests that a lot of
the tax refunds are simply going right
into the gasoline station. Uh consumers
are using the money to pay for the
higher pump prices, which means they
haven't necessarily cut back on their
spending, especially discretionary
spending just yet. But then again, we
got the data from S&P Global, especially
outside the United States, which
suggested that service providers in
particular saying, "Uh-oh, it's coming."
It may It may already be happening
places like Europe where the services
PMI for S&P Global hit a 62-month low,
but a lot of other services providers
here in the United States said, "We can
feel the winds shifting. We can feel the
consumer winds blowing." So, it really
is critical
to get a handle on this energy shock and
how sticky it is, which brings me back
to what I talked about in the
introduction here, the Dallas Fed
survey. So, the Dallas Fed survey, which
was released on Thursday, was data
collected between April 15th and 20th,
so relatively recent. They uh surveyed
120 oil and gas firms, and of those
respondents, 78 of them were in
exploration and production, which is
relevant here, and 42 of them were oil
field services firms. So, relevant
experience in the industry.
And the major question that they asked
was, "By when do you expect traffic to
the Strait of Hormuz to return to normal
levels?" 20% said May, that's the most
optimistic, so one out of five, but 39%
said August, and another 40% said either
November or later than November. So, at
the very least you've got the vast
majority saying summertime at the
earliest. And when you couple that with
the fact that the level of of supply
that has been taken off the global
marketplace is absolutely astronomical,
to not be able to restore that until uh
summertime at maybe the earliest, it is
going to be a much stickier oil
situation than I think most people are
appreciate, certainly at the stock
market. Though, Steve, you and I talked
about this, and I know you talk about
this all the time in your show. We we
fully expected the stock market to
behave like this. We said it a couple
weeks ago, it's going to rocket higher,
and it has rocketed higher. But moving
forward from here, unless the oil
situation and the energy shock really
does die down, and there is a a
legitimate solution to it, it's going to
be very it's going to be more difficult
for the uh stock market in particular to
sustain its advance uh given
given what it's been doing uh more
recently.
>> What is a Eurodollar University
membership? It's where understanding the
monetary world isn't a mystery, it's a
method. If you're serious about your
financial education, and you want
clarity in a world of volatility and
misunderstanding,
this is for you.
Mainstream education has left so many
gaps on the most foundational concepts,
making sense of everything is
practically impossible otherwise. With
our memberships, we'll fill in
everything that you've been missing.
Whether you're starting out or
sharpening your edge, our membership
scale with your goals. At Eurodollar
University, we teach you about how money
really works, so that you can evaluate
fundamentals and make grounded
decisions. With a Eurodollar University
membership, you get a comprehensive
library of foundational and advanced
lectures, in-depth case studies, and
real-world analyses, live Q&A sessions,
regular updates on macro trends, and
even some central bank policies. And
most important, how to interpret
critical derivative market signals you
will not find anywhere else.
You can't be in position to succeed if
you don't know how it all really works
and fits together. So, if you're ready
to explore master monetary systems both
past and future with structure, clarity,
and confidence. Click the link in the
description to visit
eurodollar.university/memberships
to join us today.
>> Yeah, absolutely right, Jeff, because
you know, we we look at and I would say
I think somewhere between maybe August
and the end of the year is actually a
fair assumption of what's going to
happen. But, even if flows came back,
and I think a lot of people don't
understand this, this isn't you just
like your faucet where you just go turn
it back on and everything just starts
flowing. It It's just because there's
flows going to resume, they're not going
to be at full strength. It's going to
take time. In some cases, things will
come back relatively quickly, other
things will take months, and there will
be things that take years. Some things,
they won't come back the longer this
goes because shutdowns are real issue.
But, again, you come back to the market,
you know, on April 1st, Jeff, I told you
all my subscribers on my show, I told my
clients, I reallocated all the
portfolios, I said, "Look, you have to
go long here." I went long because it's
not about the fundamentals. It's about
more systematic positioning because the
risk here isn't that the market goes up.
The risk is is what is and you nailed
it, is when does it come back down? And
we know, the longer the stretch is on,
the consumers, they can absorb this. And
we've talked about this in the past. In
a healthy economy, consumers can absorb
energy shocks. Now, we know the
economy's not healthy. You know, we we
we've laid out that case over the years
that it's on a downward trend. But, you
give people, I think the tax checks are
from what I understand about $300 more
than normal. Now, and I'll tell you,
Jeff, I really thought that if the
economy was as bad as consumers have
been saying in the sentiment surveys
that they were going to save and use it
to pay down debt. And I was shocked as I
watched the retail numbers and I'm like,
well, there's the market. That's why
it's going to go up is because consumers
are spending this. So, what it tells us
is, you know, these tax checks can buy a
couple months, but you're starting to
get out, you know, middle of August, and
we already are hearing from, you know,
consumers saying, "Look, I'm not going
to travel." Why? Gas price is too high.
You know, airfare is too high. I'm not
going to buy a new home. Why? Not
confident about my job. So, as these
things start to get a little bit bigger
and consumers cut back a little bit
more, what's going to happen is, again,
all these inventories are going to pile
back up again, and we're back where we
were before facing another inventory
recession, except this time it starts to
look a lot like stagflation where energy
prices, and this is the the big risk
where they they don't come down because,
you know, the supply and demand dynamics
have changed so much that supply has
dropped off that maybe we have
inflation, or at least energy prices
that stay elevated. At the same time,
perhaps we start to see the labor market
weakening. That is the biggest risk I
think the economy and the markets are
facing. I think people see it coming,
but the markets are saying, "Ah, we
don't really care right now."
>> Well, I think it Steve, isn't it one of
those situations where
um certainly investors in the stock
market, but just people who are paying
attention, they they hear this, right? I
mean, we've said it, other people have
said it. Look, this energy shock is
going to stick around for a long time. I
think people hear that and it makes
sense, but they don't necessarily buy
into it because, again, that the spread
between oil prices and the real economy
and futures prices, right? Yes, $100 per
barrel oil is not good, but it certainly
isn't $130 per barrel oil. And so, the
real economy right now is paying $130,
but people's perceptions are being
driven by, you know, WTI the front month
contract, which is $96, $95 per barrel.
So, it's it's it's pretty high, but it's
not extreme. And so, you keep talking
about this thing is going to linger on
for a long time. The amount of oil
that's being lost in the marketplace is
in the real physical marketplace is
absolutely staggering. But yet, WTI
seems to be hanging in around $95 per
barrel. So, there's a disconnect there
in perception. And so, that I think
feeds into a lot of the more
And it by the way,
Steve and I will talk about this in a
second. We think that's intentional. It
feeds into this idea that the oil market
is saying it looks like the oil market
is saying, "Yes, people talk about all
this stuff. It's going to It's going to
last a long time, but if we believed it,
then the oil price would be a lot higher
than it is. Therefore, the oil market
must be telling us we are in the most
optimistic case." And so, I think that's
the major misconception here is that
when you just look at the oil price
that's put up there on the screen on you
know,
thrown around in an X or so media, it's
not the one that necessarily represents
the situation that we are confronting.
It's sort of manipulated, and I think it
manipulated is the right term here cuz
you got to give the Trump administration
credit. Set aside your politics, what
the Trump administration has been doing
to manipulate the futures price of oil
has been nothing short of of you know, I
want to say genius because that's
exactly what it is.
So, it leads to this misconception where
the oil market appears to be saying or
appears to be pricing the best case
scenario. Meanwhile, the marketplace
itself over here is saying, "Holy crap,
this thing is building and building and
building and building. It's not getting
better. It's not It's not likely to get
better anytime soon." But yet, $95 per
barrel WTI futures, it looks like best
case scenario, right, Steve?
>> Yeah, Jeff. In fact, I would argue that
probably is very much the best case
scenario. And you know, if someone's
looking at the US equity market and
looking at the US economy and trying to
say, "Hey, you know, maybe this is going
to be okay." You you almost have to this
point take the entire US market out of
the picture and start looking at Europe
and Asia because they didn't have these
tax refund checks. So, consumers there
don't have extra money. And as you said,
you know, in the beginning of the show
is look at the services sector PMIs. I
mean, you know, everyone said they were
going to leave the factory sector out of
this mess and then now all of a sudden
they're the ones leading to the
downturn. But, it's all exactly what
we've been talking about Jeff is, you
know, energy prices go up at the pump,
you know, your air conditioner, your
electric bill, all that stuff. And you
have to make a trade-off. So, you start
thinking about it. Consumers are making
the trade-off on the services side and
on the factory side everybody's front
running cuz they're like, "Hey, maybe
these energy prices are going to go up
in the in the months to come. So, I want
to get as much inventory now, once
again, while things are cheap." And
that's driving the factory sector. But,
the PMIs are very interesting too
because they're like, "Hey, backlogs are
dropping, inventories are rising and we
don't think this is sustainable." So, if
I was looking at where the global
economy and the global markets are
going, I'm looking at Asia and Europe
right now. I I I mean, look, I'm long
the US market. I've been very clear
about that. I do believe it goes higher,
but my risk is when does it reverse?
That's why I'm watching the rest of the
world because I think they're going to
give us that indication far before
everyone else. And if that happens, then
oil prices are coming down. But, once
again, as we've talked about, just like
interest rates, yes, you know, everybody
wants lower interest rates, but if
they're going down it's for the wrong
reasons. I would argue the same thing.
If oil prices started collapsing on the
front month, it would tell us that
there's something wrong in the economy
that's going to drive them lower, to
demand destruction issue.
>> Well, yeah, and I think the other thing
that will correct that misper-
misperception, Steve, is right, the
gasoline prices. So, if gasoline really
does start to reflect the cash price,
which by the way, again, daily Brent's
around $130,000 per barrel, not the $100
per barrel that the futures price is at.
If you You gasoline prices that start to
diverge from the futures price in oil,
people are going to stop paying
attention to $95 WTI futures and start
saying, "What the hell's going on with
gasoline? Why is it, you know, rising?"
RBOB, which is the main wholesale future
gasoline price or gasoline price future,
that one has moved to a new high, new
multi-year high. Hasn't been this high
since, you know, energy shock in 2022.
Even though oil prices are hanging in,
RBOB is creeping higher. It's up around
$3.45 per gallon, which is an enormous
price. Again, that's wholesale. Then you
got to add taxes and everything else on
top of it to get to the retail price,
which is going to be around $4.50
heading toward $5 per gallon. So,
as the gasoline price starts to reflect
the cash price, the idea that the
best-case scenario is being priced into
the marketplace is probably going to
disappear relatively quickly. And then,
as Steve said, if you're long in the
stock market, then you have to make some
tough choices because then the world
starts to look very differently. Then
it's not, "Hey, the oil market is
relatively sanguine in pricing the
best-case scenario." It's, "Holy crap,
gasoline prices are pricing something
else that we weren't anticipating." Even
though you should have anticipated this
the entire time, given the scale of
supply disruption. And let's let's talk
about that for a second, too, uh Steve.
The reason why WTI futures and Brent
futures, for that matter, are diverging
so much from the cash price. Look, every
time the futures price goes up, uh
President Trump, and again, this is
definitely intentional. Every time the
futures price goes up, there is a tweet
or a Truth Social that comes out that
says, "Going to talk to Iran tomorrow."
or "We're doing something about getting
things going." And because everybody is
leveraged so much in the futures market,
the downside to being long in that type
of news flow risk scenario is absolutely
massive. Let me give you an example
here. There was a There was a story that
showed up in Bloomberg um
late this week. In fact, it was just a
couple days ago. Energy trader Pierre
Andurand's largest hedge fund plunged
about 52% in the first half of April,
wiping out first-quarter gains made on
bullish oil bets at the start of the
Iran Iran war. His fund slumped this
month through April 17th and is now down
almost 37% for the year, a person with
knowledge of his return said asking not
to be identified. It comes after the
Andurand Commodities Discretionary
Enhanced Fund delivered a 31% gain in
March even as other hedge funds were
caught off guard by the huge swings in
commodity prices and inflation
expectations unleashed by the war. So,
this guy is massively leveraged long oil
and what it goes to show is that if
you're on the wrong side of some kind of
presidential tweet, you can get your
butt handed to you. And that's a point
that's reminded or that's that's, you
know, it's it's nailed home every single
day in the marketplace. So, if futures
market has to reflect not just the the
upside from the fundamentals that we're
talking about, but it also has to
has to keep in mind the downside because
if the best-case scenario would would
actually develop, there is a huge
downside to oil prices. So, yes, the
futures price is being manipulated,
which means it is the longer this goes,
the less accurate that becomes and so
you're looking at the wrong market price
and you should be looking at something
like the cash prices or now gasoline.
>> And yet the same thing is true with the
stock market because look what happened
going into the you know, the ceasefire
where it was going to end. Everyone was
like, okay, the market rallied, but now
it's going to come crashing down and you
know people like, all right, I'm going
to go back and start shorting here. But
if you look at the underlying data, we
see retail investors didn't participate
in this rally. Going back to April, we
saw a lot of professional money managers
were building cash and then hedge funds
were short as they were going back to
liberation day. Now, back then they
flipped and went long. This time they
didn't. They're still almost the same
level of short positions. If you want
the market to go up, simple, you just
got to squeeze them. And so I know
people are you know, saying, "Hey, you
got to close you should close your
longs, close your longs." I'm like,
"Nope." And sure enough the next day the
market dropped and I know people are
like, "Aha!" ha, ha." Trump came out
with a tweet and it was like, "Yeah,
we're going to have a 3-week extension
or and maybe an indefinite, who knows?"
And boom, the market now Friday all-time
highs once again. It's like, "Look, they
know that the dynamic to pushing the
economy through cuz you know, nobody
knows how long this is going to go. But
if you don't think there's someone in
the Trump administration, Jeff, you know
and I know this is true, that's telling
look, if this energy shock persists,
you're going to get a recession. This is
not what you want. So, what do you've
got to do? You've got to talk oil prices
down and you've got to talk the stock
market up to keep people that are in the
market making money cuz they'll keep
spending and maybe it'll keep things
going. It might not, but that is the
short-term effect. So, yes, is the oil
market being manipulated? Yes. Is stock
market being manipulated? Yes. And are
people that are short going to get
squeezed to the upside on the market?
Yes. And those long on the oil are going
to get squeezed to the downside? You
bet. It's And if you don't think it's
happening, kick back and watch cuz we're
seeing it happen right now in real time.
>> It's a smart political play, right? I
mean, if if you're the president at this
point, what else are you going to do?
Um you've decided the Iran conflict must
be worth the political capital,
therefore you got to do whatever you can
to do to see it through. And yes,
stocks want to go up. They want to go
up, so leverage that. Leverage that that
trend. Oils oil prices need to go down
because fundamentally you take away the
Iran conflict, oil is $50 per barrel,
not 150. So, leverage that, too. The
problem for us, as Steve is pointing out
here,
you Yeah, you want to chase the stock
market returns, but understanding that
if this oil shock does stick around past
a certain threshold, which you cannot
predict ahead of time, it is going to
lead to really negative and nasty
consequences. And so,
as we go further along here, you want to
pay less attention to the manipulated
prices and more attention to the
fundamental values, which are
unfortunately not stacking up in our
favor, which brings us back to what we
said earlier with the Dallas Fed survey.
The oil shock from at least this
perspective among oil veterans looks to
be a lot stickier than people are giving
it credit for. And one reason for that
is because the amount of supply that is
being constrained is absolutely
staggeringly huge, astronomical,
whatever term you want to put into it.
And the longer it goes, the more likely
not only leads to that worst-case
scenario, to some of the bad scenarios,
it leads to more permanent damage.
Therefore, even stickier on the oil
shock. So, a recommendation here is
look, you got to understand what the
energy shock is and where it's going for
what it's what's going on behind the
scenes, which means more and more you
got to pay less attention to the futures
prices and more attention to other
prices and they're starting to make some
moves that look like the downside is
really starting to build up here.
Huge thanks to Steve as always stopping
by sharing his opinions. Private credit,
people think it's about Lehman Brothers,
especially there's a lot of stuff going
on right now, but it's not really about
a Lehman Brothers and I went over why
and what's really happening in the video
link below. As always, thank you very
much for joining me. Huge thank you Euro
Dollar University members and
subscribers and until next time, take
care.